<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bible-bearer. By A.N. sometimes of Trinity Colledge in Oxford</title>
            <author>Newman, Arthur.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113226</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848463</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1179:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Bible-bearer. By A.N. sometimes of Trinity Colledge in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Newman, Arthur.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W[illiam] I[aggard] for I[effrey] C[horlton] and are to be sold at the north doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A.N. = Arthur Newman.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-F4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:1"/>
            <p>THE Bible-bearer.</p>
            <p>By A. N. ſometimes of Trinity Colledge in Oxford.</p>
            <q>Dè Hipocritis haec Diſutatio eſt Qui mihi iraſci voluerit, ipſe dè ſe, quod talis ſit, confitebitur. <bibl>Ierom. de vita Clerec.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by W.I. for I.C. and are to be ſold at the North doore of Paules. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>worſhipfull, maiſter Hugh Browker,</hi> one of the Prothonotories of his Maieſties Court of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Pleas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vuenall</hi> in his daies complained of the multitude of writers, ſaying: —<hi>Tenet inſanabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e multos Scribendi Caco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that Patrons were wearied in protection of their labours. There be alſo many in this our age, that <hi>ad prelum tanquam ad praelium</hi> runne to the preſſe, and ſubſcribe to their indeauours: yet learning was neuer ſo friendleſſe, that ſhe ſo wearied her fauorers, but that alwayes his works ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worthy <hi>Maecenas.</hi> I haue in this litle booke diſcouered the follies of irreligious Hippocrites and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, by which the Church hath beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lipended, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beene offended, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and grieuouſly pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. God auert his future pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and turne his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice into mercy. GOD raiſe vp (eſpecially now) truſty <hi>Chuſa,</hi> prouident <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and iuſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> bold <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> playne <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, inſtant <hi>Paule,</hi> and feeding
<pb facs="tcp:13558:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:4"/>
               <hi>Peter:</hi> exploding &amp; extirpating wicked <hi>Achitophel,</hi> couetous <hi>Iudas,</hi> blind <hi>Elimas,</hi> and paltry <hi>Magus:</hi> and graunting that the fig<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leaues of Authority, Parentage, Selfe loue, flattery, and diſſembling, may bee pulled off from <hi>Madam Placentia,</hi> and the Noble Lady <hi>Verona</hi> may ſhew her liniaments in vninueſted and vnobſcured nakednes: So that with true harts &amp; pure Souls euery one may bring the Arke of God into their houſes, while they may; that their houſes may be bleſſed, as thoſe hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vvhere the Arke was: and that this famous Cittie vvith the adioyning places, now after their long infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and late ſorrovvfull ſighing of that <hi>Hei mihi quanta deſpe decidi,</hi> may (as it was ſaide of Chriſt) <hi>guſtare poſt fella fauos:</hi> to the glory of God, Church, Common-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ealth, and our priuate good.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oldned by good notice taken of your loue to Learning and vertue, to paſſe this my Labour vnder the prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion of your name. Not doubting but the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect being good, it ſhall find your fauourable and good acceptance, and bee thereby ſorovvded from the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e of Contempt. If you looke on it, and like it, my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours haue a condigne counterpoiſe. In which hope I commit your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſhip to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:4"/>
            <head>A Preface to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a Tree (ſaith <hi>Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> no fruit, the cauſe is in the ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The cauſe of the barrein leaues of peoples trec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and their vaine words, &amp; worſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, may be taken to be the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Nutrality</hi> in Religion. I haue therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to write this ſmal Treatiſe: intituled the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-bearer, diſcouering the vanity &amp; errors of ſuch as make a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ely profeſſion, yet haue no true prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Religion: that would be accounted zealous, yet are <hi>Neuters</hi> and Irreligions: becauſe this our age hath brought forth many a prodigious <hi>Polipu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and vaine ayre-full <hi>Camelions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, <hi>Si fortè mihi vitio detur.</hi> If perchance I be blamed (eſpecially of idle make bates, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Cauillers) that I haue applyed ſome writers to my owne vſe, I aunſwere them as<note n="a" place="margin">Patric. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. in lib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tir. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in.</note> 
               <hi>Patricius</hi> did the like: <hi>Me parum admodum fidei rebus meis facturum fuiſſe; Si ſolum authoritate mea in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erer.</hi> Beſides, it is the cuſtome of all Writers to mingle other mens things with their owne. <hi>Tum vt certiora ſcribant, tum vt gratius, iucundiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> legantur.</hi> Both that the truth may bee written more certainely, and that which is written may be to the Reader more grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and pleaſing. Or as<note n="b" place="margin">Idem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Aphranius</hi> being accuſed, that he had taken much out of <hi>Menander:</hi> I confeſſe (ſaith he) I haue taken not onely out of him, but out of euery one that agreed to my matter. <hi>Quodeun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> me non poſſe facere melius credidi.</hi> Onely this I feare
<pb facs="tcp:13558:5"/>that the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom I cite, may returne <hi>Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als Apoſtroph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me, <hi>Sed male dum recitas, incipit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tuum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> running through ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of his ſweetnes.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ough: for the matter it ſelfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer this meane Booke hath learned this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icere de vitijs:</hi> To ſpare the man, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouch his manners: ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome (as<note n="e" place="margin">I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his) <hi>homines male ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſſe me volent quae per ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Will thinke I meant that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> my mind. Howbeit I may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hierome.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neminem laeſi, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſig natum eſt. Neminem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</hi> I haue ſtriken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtriſe: Maligned no man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> any, but his enuy<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> people and contentious, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſe, nor doe I paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of mans iudgment, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Onely thee (gentle Reader) I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thought of <hi>Hera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouldeſt char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtand is</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> want <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſme, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> being prouoked, I haue called ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earers, Neuters,</hi> or <hi>Nullifidians,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:5"/>beare with this alſo: <hi>Ipſa enim neceſſitas adure ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus certaminis doctrinas inſtans, talem nobis ſuderem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it, et vt lectores auertantur</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Epiphan. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in lib h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t eſ.</note>. As ſaith <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not vnlike caſe. I did it, becauſe ſinfull ſchiſme, and hypocriſie is impudent: and hau ng a whoores forehead, will not bee aſhamed till wee ſpit in her face.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of which, as <hi>I</hi> cannot hope for much acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of my widowes mite, for ſome will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a thing of no value, and diſdaine to reade it: others in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or loue to the name, conſider the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not the thing: &amp; more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend others ſilence then this indeauour: ſome account mee bold, for handling ſuch matter: ſome think themſelues skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and learned, if they can detract from other mens labours, <hi>Et non quid ipſi poſſint: Sed quid nos non poſsumus, dijudicent:</hi> So may <hi>I</hi> iuſtly wiſh with <hi>Lucilius,</hi> that neither the beſt nor worſt learned might be my Readers: becauſe they vnderſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, and theſe more then (perhaps) <hi>I</hi> mean. <hi>Perſeum non curo legere, Lael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Perſeus</hi> is too learned, <hi>I</hi> wiſh honeſt,<note place="margin">Cice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de Orat.</note> and not vnlearned <hi>Laelius</hi> to be my Reader. If <hi>I</hi> haue doone well it is the thing <hi>I</hi> deſire; if ſlenderly &amp; bately, it is that <hi>I</hi> could: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer let the profit bee his that reades, the painer his that hath wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en. And this for <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Corpore vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13558:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The Speakers names</hi> ARE THEOTIMVS, and POLIPHEMVS.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Oliphemus,</hi> thou art very well met: for trauayling along the way alone, my eies preſented with no deſired obiects to feede vpon, nor my heart made happy in the fruition of any hopefull accident, I began to bee melancholy: and thy comming tenders occaſion vnto me to talke, aſwell to ſatiſfie my minde, as to beguile the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſſe of time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli</speaker>
               <p>I am glad <hi>Theotimus,</hi> that my preſence may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſure you, or profit you: for mine owne part, my Fortunes are all alike: No wind at any time blows me any comfort or commodity, but trauaile I whither I wil, <hi>Per varios caſus, &amp; tot deſcrimina rerum,</hi> I ſtill continue in <hi>eodem ſtatu:</hi> A good yeare mends me not, nor a bad pairs me ſlot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It may be ſo <hi>(Poliphemus)</hi> for that is a fate that alwaies followes men, that faſhion themſelues to time, that can play on both ſides, that can be, <hi>Verbis tenus, factis procul.</hi> Such as can holo with the Hare, and run with the Hound, and care more for a dramme of diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then a pound of plaine dealing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray thée tell me <hi>(Theotimus)</hi> what makes thée thus Criticall? Or cauſeth theſe complaints againſt the condition of Times? Is it any former obſeruation from others, or any preſent obiect from my ſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:8"/>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Why then ſéeing our way is alike, and time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents vs with like oppor tunity: before I heare mine own faults rehearſed (if at any time heretofore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haſt noted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in me) let me heare other mens blemiſhes blazed, ſuch (as thou ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſt) carry (like <hi>Ianus</hi>) two faces vnder one hood, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are men for all inanity of goodneſſe, as wels with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er: for lightnes and inſtability, as winds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raine: for barrenneſſe, trees without fruite: and for darkeneſſe, Stars without light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>The more ſhamefull that any fault is <hi>(Poliphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus)</hi> the more carefull we ſhould be to ſhunne it. And what more haynous cryme then Hypocriſie, yet what more commen then ſuch behauior? There liue now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Monſters in nature, Apoſtataes from God, Atheiſts in errour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Counterfeites of holyneſſe, that profeſſe the kingdome of the Goſpell, but for the moſt part imbrace the kingdome of the world: that are Angels in ſhew, in deeds Deuils: that are Saints in face in hart Serpents: Gods word ſwumming in their lips: but deteſtable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than digging in their ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Such are termed Atheiſts, are they not <hi>Theoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>You may call them what you will, but I think they are people worſe then Atheiſts, for the Atheiſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues to bee (as they are) openly wicked, but the other by ill diſſimulation, to be good: Whereby that ill doth more annoy vnder coulour of goodneſſe. Sweare an oath they will not, but by my truly: <hi>Indeed-la: Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as I liue,</hi> yet for all this faire ſhew, they will not ſtick to practiſe any vnderhand preiudice againſt their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: and infect the heauens with their horride and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of impieties.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>But God knoweth their ſecret intents <hi>(Theo.)</hi> doth he not? <hi>The.</hi> Thou ſpeakeſt like thy ſelfe <hi>(Poli.)</hi> better inſtructed to defend thy body with thy Weapon then to
<pb facs="tcp:13558:8"/>comfort thy ſoule with Gods word: doſt thou not know that diſſemble with the world they may, but with God they cannot? He of his knowledge cannot be deceiued: Of his truth cannot be changed: of his inuiolable faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, cannot be corrupted: For (although he permit them a while) yet doth he procéed to note downe the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineſſe of their behauiour, and at lenght giue them to know that it is in vaine to make falſe ſemblance with him: to be ready both to worſhip <hi>Baal,</hi> with <hi>Achab,</hi> and the Lord with <hi>Jehu:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reg. 16, &amp; 29. Ezr. 4. Numb 24 Math. 20, &amp; 27.</note> To build vp the Temple with <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel,</hi> and pull it down with the <hi>Aramites:</hi> To bleſſe for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and curſe for <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ak:</hi> to cry <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to day, and <hi>Crucifige</hi> too morrow, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>This ſame <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> then is a great ſin belike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is the Throne and crowne of all villany, the ſtaine and ſhame of piety, the ſcum of fallacy, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of iniquity, and conſounder of integrity. It worketh all her falſhood vnder a colour of truth, it affecteth wronges vnder a Maſke of dooing right: It performeth all manner of iniquity, vnder the Veſture of Chriſtian Duty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>It ſéemes <hi>(Theoti.)</hi> you haue béene a curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of other men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Not curious, but carefull: and not without cauſe. For it hurteth more with a vayled ſéeming veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then doth an Enimy by armed hoſtility: The one commeth into the fielde like a man, the other into the Court with falſhood, like the Deuill: the one with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in hand, the other with poyſon in hart: this aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with valour and magnanimity, that other decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by diſſembled colour and Treachery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But now tell me <hi>(Theo.)</hi> what ſaw you in me, that at the firſt gaue you occaſion to make this the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of your ſpeech?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I will reſolue you by and by, but firſt make it knowne vnto me what you wil do (<hi>Poliphe.</hi>) hunting in
<pb facs="tcp:13558:9"/>this place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli</speaker>
               <p>You aſke (methinkes) a very idle queſtion, for wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oundes haue I, I pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you, or hunting ſtaffe? See h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re my Nets, Tramell, and hunting geere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo</speaker>
               <p>What do I behold: <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chus</hi> in a Lyons caſe? My ſwagging <hi>Poliphemus</hi> with a Booke. This makes well for our firſt matter: yet you haue bin at coſt with it, it ſeemes to me to be a warlike booke, it is ſo armed, ſo painted and bound about with braſes of braſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Looke into it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee it well inough, and yet I ſée it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently furniſhed as it ought to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Looke into it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee it well inough, and yet I ſée it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fciently furniſhed as it ought to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What lackes it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhoulde haue ſet it foorth better, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h your owne Armes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What Armes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sylenus</hi> head, or an Aſſes head péeping out of a Tunne: for <hi>omnis habitus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cile ſeparabilis est a Subiesto,</hi> And becauſe thou carieſt it, methinks the ſubiect ſhould be of no other matter, but the arte of quaffing, or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly</speaker>
               <p>Take héed leaſt thou ſpeake vnaduiſedly, for <hi>3.</hi> things I haue herd) are exempt from mocking and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. The firſt is, the affaires of Princes, for they are not to be meddled with, <hi>Qua ſupra nos, nihil ad nos.</hi> The ſecond, the miſerie of them that are poore, for Fortune (chaunging) may make thy caſe like.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quem des vidit veniens ſuperbum,</l>
                  <l>Hunc dies vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, fugiens iacentem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The thirde, the Ceremonies of the Church, whcih ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits no idle, vnchaſt, or blaſphemous perſon. According to that of <hi>Vibullus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edat ab aris,</l>
                  <l>Out tul t hesterna gaudia noste venus,</l>
                  <l>Caſta plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t ſuperis: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ura cum monte venite, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:9"/>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>What is it then, any Church matter, or holie thing that thou beareſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>Is there any thinge more requiſite to be had in the church, or more ſacred, or holy thing then the Bible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Ieſu God: what hath <hi>Polyphemus</hi> to do with the Bible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>Aſke you that? What a Chriſtian hath to doe with Chriſt? <hi>Bona pars est Chriſtianiſmi velle ſier, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I thats true, if it bee <hi>Toto pectore,</hi> without Hyppocriſie or Diſſimulation. But (except thy minde be ſodainly altered, which I deſire) I thinke rather an Halbert, or a ſword and dagger, would become thy qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and perſon for if (vnacquainted) I ſhould méete thee on the ſea in theſe habiliments. I ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d take thée for a Pyrate: if on the land, for a very théefe and robber.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But this Bible teacheth we ſhould not iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man according to his outward ſhew and apearance, for as many times vnder a Ruſſet coate lurkes a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranous and cruell heart, ſo ſometimes a long lock, ſhag hayre, ſtaring Muchachio, fierce eies, a flaunting fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a ſouldiors Caſſocke, and a ſwaggring hoſe, do co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a Goſpellers minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>And why not? for the Wolues ſkinne many times doth couer the harmeleſſe ſheepe, and (if we may beléeue tales) an Aſſe is oftentimes hidden vnder a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>It ſéemes you déeme very ſtrangely of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh that as thou carrieſt this booke in thy hands, ſo thou hadſt it engrauen in thy hart. That thou wert as thou wouldſt ſeeme to be, ſound in religion, and not Neither hot, nor cold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I pray thée <hi>(Theotimus)</hi> what is it to be hot in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is to be baptized by Chriſt <hi>cum Spiritu Sancto,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:10"/>etigni, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe that haue not onely caſt off the works of darkneſſe by mortifying their owne fleſh, denying their owne ſelues, ſubduing their owne wils, for going their own delights, &amp; contemning the glory of the world, the flattrings of proſperity, and the deſpights of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, but are made infatigable againſt al labours: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trepidable againſt daungers, and inexpugnable againſt all power vſing. <hi>Tanta humilitate in Conuerſatione, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate infide veritate in verbis, iustitia in factis:</hi> Such gouernment in manners, and Iuſtice in Workes, as that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r whole liues, are Pietye: Theyr bodyes, Sanctitie: Theyr mouthes, Verity: Theyr hearts, Charity, and themſelues Myrrors of Integrity. Theſe may be ſaid to be hot in religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>How comes it, that there bee ſo few of this number? You neuer had more Teaching, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Thats true, But <hi>Non omnes Sancti, qui calcant limma Templi:</hi> Wee are now too many Biblebearers, Too many impious, that woulde ſeeme Religious, too many that vnder the ſhewe of ſacred holines ſhrowde a mulfitude of wickednes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>What is the reaſon that the Word of GOD ſo frankely, and ſo fréely taught, it fructifies no more? But many do ſtill (as thou ſaiſt) make Religion a Cloke for their euill dealing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>There be two cauſes that hinder the true loue of Religion. <hi>Worldly Riches, and Spirituall Pouertie.</hi> The one oftentimes enſuing the other. For men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurably rich, are immoderaly bent vpon the world: So toyled with Wordly Cares, that they ſcarce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite
<pb facs="tcp:13558:10"/>themſelues one breath of an Heauenly thought: Wealth makes men conceaue ſo vvell of themſelues, that what they doe, they eſteeme well done, and becauſe they haue Goodes enough, they thinke themſelues to be good enough. For Proſperity is often proude, wealth Wanton, and many times not onely Wilfull, but wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
               <p>Money is as mighty vnto miſchiefe as the Deuill himſelfe: It makes men forſake GOD, and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Religion. It can Worke Myracles, condemne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes, vanquiſh Armies, ouerthrowe Kingdomes, After mans Nature, Chaunge his Heart, peruert his will, and turne the reaſonable minde into brutiſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diuitiarum ſequela, est luxuria, ura intemperant, furor miustus, arrogantia ſuperba, &amp;c.</hi> Seeing then the vſe of Riches, is ſo daungerous, mans Nature ſo perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and the abuſe ſo impious, wee ſhoulde in our liues ſhewe the fruites of true Religion, and Chriſtianitie, not beare Bibles in our handes, and carry miſchieues in our heartes: Not ſeeme to diſpiſe the world, and yet greedilye Gape and gaze after thoſe thinges, which <hi>Poſſeſa onerant, Amata inquinant, amiſſa cruciant.</hi> That is, Burthen them that poſſeſſe them, defile them that loue them, torment them that loſe them.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nullum est pietatis in illo Corde veſtigium,</l>
                  <l>In quo ſibi Auaritia fecit habitaculum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13558:11"/>
Let vs not ſo faſhion our ſelues to the ſuperficiall and deceiuing ſhew of the world, that we neglect Heauen, and heauenly thinges:<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 3. de l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> leaſt they that doe ſée the truth, and will not, be made b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cannot. For it is a iuſt puniſhment following ſinne, that euery one ſhould loſe that gift, that he would not vſe well, when hee had it: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rectum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aecere cum poſſit, non vult, Amitiat poſſe cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But now <hi>(The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>timus)</hi> goe forward to tell mée who they be whom thou termeſt to be cold in Religion, Bibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bearers, luke warme hypocrites, or Diſſemblers. <hi>Theo</hi> I will. And thinke my labour very well beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if it may profit thee. There be thrée ſorts of people ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold in Religion, <hi>Atheiſtes, Naturall men, Epicures:</hi> The one is deſcribed to be without God, The other without Chriſt, the laſt, without any ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rke of the bleſſed ſpirit. The Atheiſt wantes the light of Nature, the Naturall man, the light of grace. The Epicure the light of the law, Whereby it comes to paſſe, that the Atheiſt is <hi>Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> without hope.<note place="margin">Rom 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 1 cor. 2, 14 Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 3.</note> The Naturall man, <hi>Erronious</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out truth: The Epicure <hi>Impious</hi> without conſcience. Him wee may tearme a formaliſt Bible bearer, that in religion is neither hot nor cold: For he that neither hath the comfort of the holy ghoſt in ſuch a degrée as a Saint, nor is ſo chill with the coldneſſe of iniquity, as an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, Is neither Saint nor Infidell. But as betwixt an Horſe and an Aſſe, is procreated a Mule: So betwixt this heate, and that coldneſſe, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngendred a <hi>Nullifidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> He that loueth in word, and in tongue, but not in deede, and in truth. Hee that is holy in profeſſion, but hollow in condition: Of a good opinion touching truth, but of an ill example touching li e. Such a one indéede as beareth the Bible in his hand, but without true zeale in his hart: as wil ſay, he is of true Religion, but is not truely Religious. Theſe men haue their Coates made
<pb facs="tcp:13558:11"/>of <hi>Linſie-Wolſie,</hi> theſe are they that plough with an Oxe and an Aſſe? theſe do ſow their land with diuers kindes of ſéedes, and are like the <hi>Griffin</hi> in the war betwéen the Birdes and the Beaſtes. To the Birdes he ſhewes his winges, to the Beaſts his féete: profeſſing ayde to both, yet ſhewing himſelfe <hi>Neuter</hi> to both: For as he by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his partaking of both natures, hath a naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility to play with both hands, ſo theſe luke-warme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, theſe Mungrell minded mixtures, are indifferent for all religions, ready to partake any, but in déed to loue none, but as luke-warme water will be ſooneſt Ice, ſo luke-warm men will be ſooneſt wicked. And as Ice will rather diſſolue, then admit warmeneſſe, ſo they will as eaſily dye as return to goodneſſe. For <hi>partim ſeruiunt Deo, partim Diabolo.</hi> Where God being angry, the Diuell ſhould haue any part, doth leaue his part, and let the Deuill take all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>You are too bitter <hi>Theotimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It may be you thinke me ſo, becauſe (happily) I touch you néerely. But it were well with you, if you were none of thoſe, that for want of heat, were cold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: nor through warmneſſe, buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> headed, but as you haue béene carefull, the booke or Bible you beare ſhould be fairely bound vp, and garniſhed with outward orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo you would be as diligent, your booke ſhould furniſh and beautifie you with true zeale, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and reach you to know your ſelfe in the Schoole of Humility.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What is that you call Humility?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is a vertue, ſpringing from the true feare and knowledge of God, the mother of Méekeneſſe; and ſiſter of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> without which no man can attaine to the knowledge, and feeling his owne miſery in <hi>Adam,</hi> and felicity in Chriſt. It teacheth vs to liue like Chriſtians, not like Pagans: to looke like a Lambe, not ſpeake like a Dragon, to throw downe and ſubiect our ſelues, to
<pb facs="tcp:13558:12"/>haue the name of God in our tongues, and the feare of God in our harts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Why is it then? That men continue ſo proud in heart, and ſo confidently wiſe in their owne imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: There were neuer better teachers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Tis true, neuer more teaching, nor leſſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: neuer more talking, and leſſe practiſing. For Men now ſtudy to ſerue all turnes, change themſelues into al formes: with a trice becomming openly Proteſtantes, ſecretly, Papiſtes: inwardly neither, outwardly both. Our liues worſe then our forefathers who liued in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, for in truth they knew very little, yet did very much: But we haue filed tongues, but defiled heartes: the more good we know, the leſſe we do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I will indeauour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the ſame be reformed in my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I pray God you doe, and that you vſe not as heretofore you haue done, to be a Booke-bearer, a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit of holineſſe, a Saint in honour, and a Diuell in demeanor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But leauing to be thus Criticall, doe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them which beare the Bible about them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>No. But as hee that did beare Chriſt, was called <hi>Chriſtofer.</hi> So you of bearing your Byble, ſhall be called <hi>Bibliofer</hi> a <hi>Bible-bearer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you not thinke it then an holy thing to carry the Bible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>No. Vnleſſe you will confeſſe that Aſſes bee holy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>For one Aſſe will carry <hi>500.</hi> ſuch bookes, and A thinke you are as well able to carry as many, béeing as well bridled, and Sadled, and Spurred forward, as commonly an Aſſe is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>Yet is it no abſurdity, to attribute holyneſſe to the Aſſe which carried Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:12"/>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I do not enuy you this holineſſe, if therefore you will, I will giue you a relique of the ſame Aſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>you gibe at mee, yet your gift ſhould not diſpleaſe me, for that Aſſe by touching Chriſt, was conſecrated, and made holy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Then belike they were holy that buffetted him, for no doubte they toucht him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But ieſt not. Is it not a holy thing to beare about one the Bible or Gods holy word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is, if it be truely done, without Hypocriſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Let Monkes and Fryers be Hypocrites, what haue I to do with it? Firſt then tel me what is hypocriſie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>It is a curſed and capitall crime, It is the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſanctity, and maſſacre of verity: Helles ſacring, Heauens vnhallowing. <hi>Medea</hi> confeſſeth that ſhe could by the help of <hi>Hecate, Ripis mirantibus, amnes in fontes redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſuos fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re,</hi> By her incantation make Riuers run back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes againe into their Fountaines, turne ſtreames backward, and rootes of trées vpwardes: A thing very prodigious: but this ſinne of Hypocriſie (that makes ſhew of that which is not) can do a great deale more then that: For wheras ſhe could only enchant by her charms, Riuers, hils, woods, herbs, ſtones, &amp;c. This couers <hi>Neroes</hi> cruelty vnder <hi>Catoes</hi> grauity: and <hi>Herods</hi> butchery with <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts ſimplicity. This cauſeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carrie in their harts vntrue thoughts, in their mouthes Hony, in their minds Gal. Hypocriſy maketh truth (vnder a falſe ſhew) her cloake to couer all her abhominations, ſo that ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the very heaues with the breath of her mouth, the very aire with the venom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of her tongue, and ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Hell with the malice of her hart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But what pretendes this carrying of the Bible? Doth it not betoken a Goſpel like mynde, or holy heart?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, where the life, and conuerſation agrées with the Goſpell, or Gods word, and where it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Is it not Hypocriſie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:13"/>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>It ſéemes ſo: But what is it truly to bear the word of God, or the Bible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Some carry it in their hands, as the Fryers of Saint <hi>Frauncis,</hi> do S. <hi>Frauncis</hi> rules of their order: So can Aſſes and Pack horſes do: Some in their mouthes, hauing at euery worde, Chriſt, and Gods word, which is Pharyſaicall: Some in their mindes, or by roat. But he caries it truely, that in his hands, in his mouth, and in his hart caries it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>yet for all that, they are not all holy, which haue the Bible in their minds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Play not the Sophiſter with mee, none hath it in minde, that doth not inwardly loue it; nor doeth any man loue it, that in his life, behauiour, and conditions doth not expreſſe, and obey it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I do not well vnderſtand theſe high matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I will tel you more plainly. If you carry on your ſhoulders a bottle of good Rheniſh wine, or ſweete Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadine, what other is it then a burthen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing els.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>If you hold it in your mouth, and preſently ſpit it out, what then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>It doth no good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>But if you drinke well of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>There can be nothing more heauenly, or better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>It warmes your bodie, Cheeres your counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and makes you merry, and ioyfull, doth it not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>It doth ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Such is the Goſpell or Gods worde, for being once digeſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it changeth the whole habit of a man, and reuiueth (or rather reneweth him.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Do you think I liue not acording to Gods word or the Goſpell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>No man can tell better then your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>If the matter were to be decided with my ſword.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>What if a man ſhould to thy face call thée ſlaue,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:13"/>or giue thée the lie, what wouldſt thou do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould kill him, or ſoundly beat him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>yet this booke that you beare, teacheth you to render for euill good, and to turne thy lefte chéeke to him which ſtrikes thée on the right.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I did read it, but I forgat it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>you pray often I am aſſured: Do you not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>That is Pharyſaicall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>It is Pharyſaicall to pray long, and not from the heart, but your booke willes you to pray, and that from your ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I do ſometimes pray.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>When?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>When it comes into my mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>What prayer doe you then vſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>The Lords prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>How often?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Once: for the goſpell forbiddeth vs <hi>Battology,</hi> that is, repeating one thing often.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Can you with attenſion ſay al the Lords praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I neuer tride it. Is it not inough y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I pronounce it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>No, if it bee onely with the tongue, for God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and heares the voice of the heart. Do you faſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>But your booke, enioyns you to faſt and pray.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>What good doth faſting?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>It ſerueth to <hi>3.</hi> ſpeciall good ends, firſt to mortifie and ſubdue the fleſh: Secondly to ſtirre vp our minds to meditation and prayer. Thirdly, to bee a Teſtimony of our inwarde humility, and dutifull obedience to the will of God. We ought to faſt to kéepe our bodies from ſurfetting, and our ſoules from ſinning. The diſeaſes of the minde (ſaith an holye Father) are healed with praying, and the luſtes of the body with faſting. For euen as a wanton pampred horſe doth ſtriue to caſt his
<pb facs="tcp:13558:14"/>Ryder, ſo doeth a Wanton pampred body by Nature reſiſt againſt vertue. It is good to faſt (ſaith Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>) but better to giue Almes. When the luſtes of our fleſh are mortified, our Wronged brother ſatiſfied, and our néedye neighbour reléeued, then GOD with our faſt is well pleaſed.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Sermon in the wildernes ſayth:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The ſicke for lacke of ſtomack faſt,</l>
                  <l>the poore fot want of meate,</l>
                  <l>The couetous chuffe to ſpare his purſe,</l>
                  <l>the glutton more to eat:</l>
                  <l>The Apiſh Hipocrite for praiſe,</l>
                  <l>a good man for his ſoules eaſe.</l>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I could like well of faſting (for it would ſaue mée much money to eat leſſe) but that my ſtomacke and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call ſtill for meat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>But Paule ſaith, they cannot ſerue Chriſte, that ſerue their bellies, you eate fleſh euerie day, do you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>When I can get it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>But your ſtrong-ſence-like-body is taught to plucke downe the pride of the fleſh, if it be with féeding on hay, or barkes of trées.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>But Chriſt ſaith, a man is not defiled with that which goeth into his body, or enters into his mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>If we féed moderately without offending.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>This ſhall profitte me, and teach mee to refraine from inordinate diet and drinking.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh it might. But hath thy booke yet taught thée to know what thou art?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>I am a Man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>What man is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I will then tell thee, he is a Mirrhor of miſery, a playe of Fortune, and a prey of death: Hee is borne wéeping to ſhewe his wretchednes, hee liueth laughing
<pb facs="tcp:13558:14"/>and toying, to bewray his folly, hee dyeth ſighing, and ſobbing to declare his infirmity. <hi>Oh homo</hi> (ſayth <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>) <hi>ſi conſideras quid peros, quid per nares, quid per cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros meatus egrediatur, nunquam vilius Sterquilinum inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſti.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po,</speaker>
               <p>What profit is it to me to know what man is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothing more néedefull to man, nor more neceſſary to ſuppreſſe and ſubdue his haughty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, then continual remembrance what he is, from whence he came, and whether he ſhall. That in calling to minde his baſe mettle, his Wretched condition, and mortall generation, he may the rather be mooued more humblye and lowly to conceyue and eſteeme of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Thou mighteſt do well then <hi>(Theotimus)</hi> to tel me what the world is, for I am ſure there is much villany in that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>What the world is? Hir myrth is nothing but ſorrow: her pleaſure pain: her wiſedom fooliſhnes: and her wealth miſery: pinching ſome with pouerty, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing with miſery, aduauncing the proud and vicious without deſert, deiecting the Humble and Veriuous without cauſe: befrending the froward and ſeditious, and moleſting the quiet and obedient: permitting the ignorant and fooliſh to ſpeake, and putting to ſilence the wiſe and diſcréete: extolling crafty diſſemblers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing ſimple innocents.</p>
               <p>The worlde <hi>(Poliphemus)</hi> tormentes ſome vvith ſtrife and contention: ſome with ſickneſſe, ſores, and diſeaſes. Inſomuch that if an olde man would ſet down the Tragedie of his life (from the day of his byrthe till his departure to his graue) a man woulde wonder that the body could ſuffer, and the hart could beare ſo painful and dolorous a pilgrimage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Why is it then that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſo bad, men put ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:13558:15"/>affyance in her, and are ſo eaſily ſeduced by her ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>The firſt cauſe is, Couetouſneſſe, which (as a Reuerend Father ſaith) <hi>Colit Idola, quae finxit:</hi> for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the eternall Maieſty is onely mighty, wiſe, bountiful, rich, bleſſed, and full of all goodneſſe. Now the Miſer ſaith, it is my Mony that can doe all thinges, therefore the moſt mighty, prouide all thinges, therefore moſt wiſe: giue all thinges, therefore moſt bountyfull, purchaſe all thinges, therefore moſt rich; cauſe a man to liue in all plenty, therefore moſt bleſſed.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is our owne corruption and deformity through <hi>Adams</hi> fall. Since which time, the nature of man is ſo fraile, the occaſions vnto euill ſo many, and the illuſion of Sathan ſo prompt, and ready that (except Gods ſpeciall grace preuent him) he is apt vpon euery light occaſion to be drunke with the dregs of the world, and to yéeld vnto ſinne and wickedneſſe, being more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily brought to conceiue an error by one litle word, then the truth by a long tale, and ſooner ſeduced to conſent vnto vice by one ſmall example, then conuert vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by many vehement perſwaſions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe Reſolutions of thine haue done me more good, then my booke as yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I thought what a <hi>Bible-bearer,</hi> what a ſound profeſſour I ſhould finde you? I tolde you, you would prooue one of thoſe that carry your Booke and frequent Sermons more for faſhion of the world, then loue to the word. But do you liue chaſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Happily I ſhall do when I am old. But ſhall I confeſſe the truth vnto thée <hi>Theotimus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I am no Prieſt. If you will bee confeſt, ſéeke ſome other, or rather confeſſe vnto God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Why then <hi>(Poliph.)</hi> know I am not yet a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Goſpeller, but one of the common ſort. We Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers (I meane our fraternity) doe eſpecially hunt after
<pb facs="tcp:13558:15"/>foure thinges.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Firſt, to fill our bellies.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secondly, to feede our luſts.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thirdly, to haue liuing.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fourthly, to be vncontrould, or to do what we liſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay true indéed, there be many y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> challenge to themſelues the addition of pure profeſſors, who ſtriue to liue as they liſt, and thinke it a burthen and ſeruitude to ſubmit their necks and ſoules to the yoake of humain obedience, but holde that a Chriſtian mans liberty is to liue as he pleaſe and for this cauſe ſome haue refuſed to receiue che Lords Supper knéeling, &amp;c. They will not (for ſooth) bee drawne vnder the yoake of mans power, but are of ſuch a peruerſe nature, as that they would not onely take vnto themſelues liberty in thinges indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, but indeauour alſo to croſſe the cuſtomes of the Church: For ſome haue ſent their Seruants to Plough and Cart vppon the very feaſt day of the Natiuity of Chriſt, which wee commonly call Chriſtmaſſe day, to croſſe the cuſtome of the Church of England, which kéep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it holy.<note place="margin">Oxfords anſwer &amp;c.</note> Others (as appeareth by <hi>Oxfords</hi> anſwer to their Petition exhibited to the King) <hi>Did ſpend the fift of Auguſt 1605 in faſting,</hi> to croſſe that authority which commaunded them to celebrate it with ioy and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his maieſties ſtrange deliuerance from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of the Earle of <hi>Gowry.</hi> There is another ſociety of men, who in the time of Lent, were wont to eate fleſh ſeuen daies in the wéek, though out of Lent but fiue, and I thinke they did it to no other ende but onely to croſſe the authority of that power, which enioynes them from eating of fleſh meat at that time of the yéere. Thus they behaue themſelues (in déede) like men that labour to liue vncontrouled. They will be euer in an ertreame, for when we feaſt, they will faſt: and when we faſt they will feaſt: And carry to the cie of the world ſuch a ſéeming
<pb facs="tcp:13558:16"/>ſhew of ſauctify, that (vnleſſe a man be well acquainted with their manners and conditions) they are able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a very well taught and grounded experience. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I knew <hi>(Poli.)</hi> thou art able to iuſtifie of thy ſelfe in thy obſeruance of their beheauiours ſince thou haſt béene a Bible-bearer, I meane a profeſſor in ſhew, not in déede, if thou wouldeſt but diſcouer their abſurdities which I thinke very fit for a Caution and inſtruction to others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I am not yet <hi>(Theo.)</hi> ſo reſolued a profeſſor, but that good and holeſome perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may preuaile w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mee, for (methinkes) I cannot relliſh our Teachers doctrine, nor do I like their impugning of the magiſtracy,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tan. to England Page 92.</note> nor their exhorting the common people to repute thoſe Princes for Gods Enimies, that liue not vnder the yoake of their pretended holy Diſcipline.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>I make no doubt but thou wilt grow into a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of their dealings, for they haue depraued and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not onely the common book, but the whole eſtate of the Church as it was reformed by her late maieſty. Yea in her maieſties life time, the ſtate of this church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was ſo depraued beyond the Seas, by new fangle <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſciplinartans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Qualter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcop l li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſi an. 1574.</note> as that it hath béene conceiued by very godly and Religious men in forreigne Countries, that we haue no lawes, no good orders, no diſcipline, but that euery man may do what he liſt. They refuſe to ſubſcribe to the Kings lawfull authority, in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, to the Articles of Religion, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Book of common prayer, and the orders rites and Ceremonies of our Church. Nay they diſſent from vs in thinges accidentall and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall. For example ſake,<note place="margin">Pet. Mart. in Epiſt. 3. Beza in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. 8, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2</note> the Cappe, and the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe &amp;c. are <hi>Adiaphora,</hi> that is, thinges in different in their owne nature, yet are there many of ſo peruerſe a condition that rather then they will weare them, they will loſe their liuings, and forſake their callings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>They are not of my minde, for in my opinion
<pb facs="tcp:13558:16"/>that is then great folly and inſolency. Had I a good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing I ſhould willingly vſe thoſe matters, being things ſo indifferent, before I ſhould forgoe my meanes by ſuch a madneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bulling ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. fo. 18 102.</note>But who haue they cryed out againſt benificed-men, ſaying they were <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entris minſtra,</hi> Miniſters of the belly, and that they could not teach truely, becauſe of their great liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo</speaker>
               <p>The onely thing I think <hi>(Poli.)</hi> they aymed at, was that the Paſtors might be expelled, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo they might ſuccéede them. <hi>Swinglius</hi> ſaith, <hi>They teach that ſuch can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preach the Goſpell ſincerely,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zuingl. in Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
                  <hi>which haue great benifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: But then hope is to haue the true Paſtors expelled, that they may ſucceede in their places: And yet forſooth they publikely proteſt, they ſeeke for no liuing.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray thée fell me <hi>(The)</hi> that I may profit by thée? how long h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h the Surpleſſe beene vſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>npioribus eccleſiaſt.</note>The Godly fathers of the Church in the pureſt eſtate therof, haue left it in writing, that the Miniſters in their times did vſually put on white garments, in the celebration of the Sacramentes, and execution of diuine Seruice.</p>
               <p>Nay it was vſed in the very day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Apoſtles, as is teſtified by <hi>Hegeſipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who (as an holy Father ſaith) liued néere the Apoſtles time. His Teſtimony is this,<note place="margin">Hegiſip. li. comment linea, no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea veſte induauatur.</note> 
                  <hi>When Iames ſirnamed Iuſtus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> went into the Temple, he was apparelled with a linnen veſture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>This ſhall ſuffice me for that queſtion, but why do our teachers tel vs that the Croſſe in baptiſme is a piece of Popery?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Therein they commit a fallacy, for it was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church within the compaſſe of <hi>300</hi> yéeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, and hath béene vſed euer ſince.<note place="margin">Dyon. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cop. de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. ca. de baptiſmo.</note> Beſides the writinges of many fathers, that iuſtifie the ſame, <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius Areopagita,</hi> who liued in the Apoſtles tyme,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:17"/>maketh mention of the Croſſe in baptiſme, why do they finde fault with the Ring in the ſolemnization of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raige?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>They are too nice in their points. The ring in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mony is an auncient Ceremony. For <hi>Tertullian</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ued almoſt <hi>200.</hi> yeares before Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> time maketh mention of it. Therefore <hi>Zanchye</hi> ſpeaketh in our behalfe for the vſe thereof,<note place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Reſexternae, &amp;c. <hi>Things exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nall which are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t repugnant to the word, and which neither are Superſtitious, nor obſcene, are to be obſerued acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rding to the Cuſtome of the Countrey wherein wee liue.</hi>
                  </hi> But many make ſhewe of zeale, where there is none: affecting new formes, Inuenting new opinions, and running from errour to errour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>What thinke you the cauſe that many haue ſo run from one newe opinion to another, and are of no more ſlayed and ſetled a iudgement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The</speaker>
               <p>I coniecture it to bee, becauſe they haue contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and diſdained the auncient fathers of the church, and haue thought it the looſing and miſpending of good hours to pervſe their writinges. For one of them being vrged (for his conformity) with the Teſtimonies of the Claſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and principall Doctors of the Church,<note place="margin">T. C li. 1 pag. 154</note> cried out, that <hi>Truth <hi>was meaſured by the crooked yard of Tyme,</hi>
                  </hi> and termed the ſéeking into the Fathers writings, <hi>A taking in duches, and that his harty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>xed cold, and his fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to heare m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t a Preacher ſhould quote Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alledge P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Philoſophers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem. li. 1. pag. 1.4</note> 
                  <hi>and confirme hys matter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of hum ne vvriters. And yet Paule himſelfe doth alledge <hi>Aratus, Menander,</hi> and <hi>Epime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ides,</hi> who were all He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>en P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke that warrant enough, and ſufficient. But what is the reaſon then, that ſince my late conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with ſome of them, I haue hearde ſuch exceptions taken againſt Poets and Philoſophers, and the fathers
<pb facs="tcp:13558:17"/>whom they ought rather to reuerence (with <hi>Seneca</hi>) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>(Ego illos ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eror, &amp;c)</hi> and to do a kind of homage to their very names?<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 3. contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian ca. 16</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>I am thus conceipted of them, that as <hi>Petilian</hi> diſpraiſed <hi>Logicke,</hi> and <hi>Rhetoricke,</hi> becauſe hee himſelfe had no ſkill in theſe Artes: So many <hi>New-fangle-Noui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> contemne all <hi>Gentile</hi> learning, and finde faulte with ſuch as make vſe of it, becauſe they themſelues are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant therein: Reſembling the Fox, that diſpiſeth the <hi>Grape,</hi> that himſelfe cannot reach: or rather like that old <hi>Foxe,</hi> that by a miſchaunce hauing loſt his tayle, went preſently to other Foxes, and perſwaded euery one of them to cutte off hys Taile, pleading that it was to weightie and Cumberſome, &amp;c. But the matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in queſtion, and to be thoroughly ſcanned, it vvas founde that the ſubtle Fore did it ſo couer hys owne deformity, which ſhould neuer haue beene eſpied, if it had once become a faſhion, or cuſtome to bee without Tailes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But note vnto mee I praye thee ſome of the Qualities, and conditions of their <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, I meane ſuch as are of the Vulgar ſort, ſuch as thou tearmeſt faſhionarie <hi>Bible-bearers,</hi> that will goe ſixe or ſeauen Miles to heare one of their owne Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and returne home ready to do miſchiefe to theyr neighbours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Their followers <hi>(Polyphemus)</hi> behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, according to that Image of the worlde that I haue ſeene pic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ured with the feete vpward, importing that all thinges are turned vp ſide downe.</p>
               <p>The very Cobbler in theſe dayes, although hee bee taught and warned, <hi>Ne ſutor vltra Crepidam,</hi> and that his Art forbiddes him to go aboue the latchet, will yet finde fault and condemne the Workmanſhippe of the thigh of the Picture.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13558:18"/>
The very Butcher, whoſe ſkill reacheth no further then the opening and cutting vppe of an Oxe, will yet aſſume the cunning to Anotamize a man. The proude Taylor, that hath ſerued a Prentiſhippe onely to learne the faſhioning of Garmentes, will take vppon him to teach Preachers to ſhape their Sermons to ſute his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               <p>The Cooke whoſe whole learning lies in the Kitchen and Larder-houſe, will bee ſawcy and meddle with the order of the Church. The Smith whoſe Art extends it ſelfe no further then his forge, will yet be ſo bolde as to blow the Coales of Contention into the Church, and ſo forge newe Opinions vppon the <hi>Anvile</hi> of errour: yea many will carpe at the Churches Gouernement, and blame the life and dealinges of other men, when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are farre Worſe, and altogether vnable to giue good directions to their owne ordinary<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affaires, yet doe they beare the Worlde in hande, that whatſoeuer they doe, they doe it being mooued thereunto by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>But to ſuch I could wiſh milder Spirits, and that they would not meddle ſo much in other Mens callings and ſo little in their owne: but that they woulde learne how dangerous a thing it is, to goe beyond the limmits and Precinctes of theyr Profeſſions, and to leaue theyr preiudiciall and obſtinate mindes, being firſt content to trye all thinges, and then afterwards to holde faſt that which is good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>By your ſpéeches then it appears, that it were better for vs, if we were all of one mind, and of one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>(Poliphemus)</hi> So it ſtandeth with the Truth, for <hi>Aequalitas prima pars est aquitatis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca in Epiſt.</note> Equality is the
<pb facs="tcp:13558:18"/>firſt, and chiefe part of Equity. And it is not good as (<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſaith) to be buſy in a wel ordred ſtate. It is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that one people, within the ſaid Land,<note place="margin">Senecain Tripod.</note> and vnder the ſame gouernment ſhould be vnder diuers opinions, but be all ledde by one Law and rule. It is the ſayings of <hi>Curtius,</hi> and it may be helde an Oracle for Truth, that <hi>Eiuſdem iuris eſſe debent, qui ſub ecdem Rege victuri ſunt.</hi> They ought to be vnder one law, that are vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of one King.<note place="margin">Curtius lib. 10</note> It is alſo the Iudgement of the Fathers, that ſuch as liue in the ſame Church togither, ſhould be vnder Law indifferently, and bee enforced by the Lawe to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modate themſelues to the cuſtomes of the place wherein they liue. <hi>In his rebus</hi> (ſaith one of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.) <hi>de quibus nihil certiſtatuit Scriptura divina mos popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Dei, vel inſtituta Maiorum pro lege tendenda ſunt.</hi> Another holdeth it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rye méete that Eccleſiaſticall Traditions, (namely ſuch as do not hinder faith) ſhoulde be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt. 86</note> as they are deliueréd of our Eldérs: and that the cuſtome of one ſhould not be ouerthrown with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary cuſtomes of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hemingius</hi> holdeth it an heinous ſinne to break the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Church. <hi>Qui violat</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Politiam, peccar multis modis.</hi> Yet many now adaies, forgetting to knowe that it is frée for euery Church to make a forme of Diſcipline or policie fit and profitable for it ſelfe, becauſe the Lorde hath preſcribed no certainety in this behalfe, (like diſtempering humours) haue gone about to alter the ſtate of this myſticall body, which whether it be the puſſe of <hi>Ambition</hi> in ſome, who like <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> woulde haue preheminence, <hi>Qui quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam non poſſunt primum loum in Exccleſia obtimere, idcirco illam ſcindunt, vel ab e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dificiunt,</hi> Or the pricke of theyr owne priuate Spirite, who would haue all thinges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theyr owne minds, ſure I am, the Deuil hath
<pb facs="tcp:13558:19"/>inuented Schiſmes, to ſubuert faith, corrupt verity, and rent vnity, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quos detinere non potuit via veteris caeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, deciperet noui itin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ris errore.</hi> That them, whom hee could not keeps in olde blindneſſe, he might deceiue with new opinions and errors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>But whence grow theſe waries and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that men for wearing of a Surpliſe, bury their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in a Napkin? That they ſtand on a corner Cappe, as on a corner ſtone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That they trouble Chriſts Spouſe for a Ring in marriage, and refuſe to preſent her as a chaſt Virgin to Chriſt? That for the croſſe in Baptiſme they leaue the Fountaine of liuing water, and become ſuch enimies to the Croſſe of Chriſt Ieſus, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>From hence they procéede <hi>(Poli)</hi> euen of their luſts (as Saint Iames ſaith) that fight in their members, <hi>They luſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ian. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and haue not:</hi> They enuy and haue indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe they cannot obtaine: they fight and warre, becauſe they get nothing. They would and will not: thou diſſemble ambition vnder the cloake of diſlike: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the maiſter of the feaſt bids them not, <hi>Friend ſit vp higher,</hi> as of ſome heere, in his daies ſpeaketh <hi>Ioannes Saribur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſis</hi> And we haue many a <hi>Iohn,</hi> who if he could be <hi>Sarisbur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſis,</hi> would preach the faith which before hée deſtroyed, and retract like <hi>Paule,</hi> when I was a little one I ſpake like a Childe, I vnderſtood as a Child: I thought as a Child: but when I becauſe a man I put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way childiſh thinges, &amp;c. But it were a happy thing, that they would conforme themſelues, and be obedient to the Church, for many by factious behauiour are drawne to be our aduerſaries. It cauſeth much griefe, and bringes great ſorrow to Gods Church, when Sonnes fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Father, greene heads againſt gray hayres, and men of yeſterday, preſume to croſſe antiquity. As they of <hi>Athens</hi> ſaide truely of their diuiſions, <hi>Auximus phil p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on bus,</hi> ſo we ſtrengthen the Pope,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:19"/>and <hi>Phillips</hi> faction by theſe our diſſentions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What is the reaſon that <hi>in rebus tam multis conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, etim vita tam in explicabile diſſidium?</hi> In ſo many thinges fellowſhip, and in life no friendſhip?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is for this, that men for wealth will be Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and diſſemble Religion carry books to ſhew an inward, zeale, and yet being (all one body) in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers no Sympathy: being al <hi>one ſpirit,</hi> and in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no harmony: <hi>All one hope of heauen,</hi> and in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs no <hi>Symphony: All one Lord,</hi> yet in fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants no vnity: <hi>All one faith,</hi> yet in opinions no <hi>Simine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie:</hi> All ſworne in one Baptiſme, yet in fellow Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors no <hi>Symmac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic:</hi> All adopted by <hi>one father,</hi> yet in brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much diſcord, and no fraternity. Thus riches en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting the minde, cauſeth a man to thinke himſelfe wiſe when he is but fooliſh, ſtrong when he is but weak, fenced when hee is but naked, to leaue the true Tower, and ſtrength of his defence, and to truſt in the weak and rotten walles of wealth.</p>
               <p>For mans nature is compoſed of two contraries, of a mortall body, the Earth, and an eternall ſoule which is from heauen; and they are as contrary as Heauen and earth: whileſt either of theſe parties, are naturally moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to conſerue the good of his owne nature. It commeth to paſſe, that both this baſe and earthly part drawes a man vehemently to be attent vpon earthly things, and contrary to that diuine and heauenly part doth couer to carry men vp into heauen from whence he is deſcended: by meanes of which repugnancy in mans nature, it is brought to paſſe, that man is wonderfully drawne into
<pb facs="tcp:13558:20"/>contrary deſires: endeuoring to ioyne things together, which of their owne nature are ſeuered fartheſt aſunder, wearying himſelfe with infinite toyle, how to ioyne with God, and the world together. To partalie of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall pleaſures, and ſpirituall ioyes: To poſſeſſe the proſperity of earth, and the felicity of Heauen: This is the cauſe of ſo little faith amongeſt Men, or diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hypocriſie, and all Neutrality at this day: For many would faine bee Chriſtians, and worldlings too: worſhip God, and <hi>Mammon</hi> too: Taſt the ſwéetneſſe of Heauen, and of the earth, and ſo would be <hi>Neuters,</hi> that is, hot and cold too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Are there many of this ſort, thinke you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Too many <hi>(Poli.)</hi> both men and Women, that like the <hi>Ambidexter Gebionites</hi> play on both ſides, and halt betwéene opinions: If the head bee for their profit, they goe after it: If the eie, they goe after it: And theſe <hi>Neuters,</hi> (or rather <hi>Vters</hi>) are like thoſe <hi>Sea-Calues, Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadiles, Otters,</hi> and <hi>Sea-Colts,</hi> in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Pliny,</hi> which are one while in the water, another while on the land, for greater booty: iuſtly tearmed <hi>Dubia</hi> by <hi>Iſodoro,</hi> becauſe you cannot tell where to haue them: Sometime they are <hi>Natatilia,</hi> and ſwim with the tide, other ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Greſſabilia,</hi> and go back for aduantage: but amongſt many there are few found, that ſide neither to the right hand, nor the left, but go ſtraight forward without Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Are there women alſo that are ſhew-carrying Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-bearers, Hypocrites, and diſſemblers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:20"/>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>(Po.)</hi> and that ſexe is very dangerous. There are many that to bee reckoned religions, frequent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, haue their Bibles fayrely bound, and hanging by their ſides, when they cannot ſo much as read them, much leſſe haue them imprinted in their hearts. Theſe maſke their euill vnder a vaile of purity, and vnder a faire ſhew ſhadow much miſchief. Their eies are ſnares, their wordes charmes, their deceite much, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires more. Their conſciences like a Pumyce-ſtone, light and full of holes, for lucre prone to change to any humor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>What is the puniſhment aſſigned for ſuch New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Hypocrites, or diſſembling Bible-bearers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>The paine is no leſſe then to <hi>be vomited out of the Lordes mouth.</hi> That is, that all Neuters for their Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and diſſimulation, ſhould be caſt out of fauor with the Sonne of GOD, which is a wofull and importable chaſtiſement, if wee conſider his diuine Nature rightly, what the ſon of God is, namely that he is the ſame God that is vnto vs the cauſe of our béeing, the Fountaine of life, and the founder of all ioy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Is that onely meant by <hi>Vomiting?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>No, By this <hi>vomiting</hi> is meant more then a bare eiecting out of fauour: For therein is expreſſed a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and violent caſting out in anger: In this <hi>Simile</hi> the Church is compared to the ſtomack: The Luke warme Newter or Hypocrite, to the Luke-warme Water,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:21"/>and their grievous diſturbance to noiſome vomitings.</p>
               <p>The Church is compared to the ſtomack, becauſe as the ſtomack b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> altering and concocting the nouriſhment receiued, feedeth and preſerueth the partes of the bodye: So the Church by concocting and diſgeſting the foode of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, doeth nouriſh and preſerue the body of Chriſt, euen in ſuch ſort, as from out of food in the ſtomacke the liuor draweth blood: the hart, Spirit: the braine, Sence: the ſinnewes, ſtrength: the vaines, noriſhment: the body, life: So out of the food of immortality (which is the word of God) that is in the church, to euery member of Chriſt doth the hart draw faith: the will, obedience: the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, knowledge: the conſcience, Comfort: the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, immortality: and the ſoule, all felicity. And that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo after ſo rare, and ſtupendious an order, that euen as the ſtomacke: So doeth it quicken by killing: reuiue by deſtroying: grow wiſe, by fooliſhnes: obey, by rebelling againſt it owne fleſh: obtaine life, through death: felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through miſery: and eternity, out of mortality.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Why is the Newter, or Hypocrite, compared to Luke warme water?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>For that luke-warm water to a faſting ſtomack (being receiued) is hurtfull: while it remaineth is grief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and being eiected is ſhamefull. Became all New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Hypocrites are euen ſuch in Gods Church, not onely by hindring the work of Gods ſpirit in the church, but by the vnquieting and diſturbing of the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13558:21"/>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>Why are their diſturbings compare to noiſome vomitings?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe, as that which bréedeth vomiting, is caſt out with hatred, for that it is enemy to Nature: with violence becauſe it oppreſſeth the ſtomack: with ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, becauſe the defilings thereof are laid open to the eie: and laſtly ſo eiected, as neuer againe to be receiued: So al Hypocritical Bible-bearers, al incorrigible New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhal: by the Lorde himſelfe bee throwne out of the Church, as filthy vomitings out of the ſtomacke, and that with hatred: becauſe they are enemies to Chriſte, and deceiuers of his people: with violence, becauſe they hurt and oppreſſe the Church: with ſhame, becauſe their Hypocriſie ſhall be made knowne: and laſtly caſt out of the Church, neuer againe to be receiued: becauſe while they were in the Church they could neuer be amended. Thus the hatred of eiection doeth ſhewe the deteſtation of the Crime: the violence, the mightines of the paine: The ſhame, the horrour of Confuſion: And the neuer receiuing, the eternity of deſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>But theſe Hypocrites (perhaps) will ſay as much by others as you ſay by them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>Not vnlike ſo: for they are apt enough to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie theyr owne weakenes: but I may anſweare them with the Poet, <hi>Oh maior tandem parc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> inſane minori:</hi> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt caſt out the beame,<note place="margin">Horat. lib. 2. Sat. 3</note> the beame in thine own eye, and then afterwarde thou ſhalt ſee clearely to caſt
<pb facs="tcp:13558:22"/>out the moat that is in ours: They are full of woundes themſelues, yet vpbraide vs with Scarres: They tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vs from ſlipping, when themſelues fall downe headlonge: They are couered with myre, and yet tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt our ſpots.</p>
               <p>They are as full of diſſentions in their own errors, as euer were the Heathens in theyr Paganiſme: <hi>Et quet ſunt Sodalitia tot ſunt factiones.</hi> As <hi>Eraſmus</hi> well obſerued: ſo many orders, ſo many factions: ſo many men, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny minds.</p>
               <p>If they vpbraide vs with Schiſmes, or Contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of opinions: I may bandy that obiection backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and aunſwere them as <hi>Demaratus</hi> did <hi>Phillippe</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who aſking him tauntingly: How doe yes <hi>Gracians</hi> agrée at <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> when himſelf was fallen out with his wife and his owne Sonne. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede thou doeſt well (quoth he) <hi>Phillip</hi> to enquire of our Concorde. <hi>Qui familiam tuam tanta patris ſeditione, &amp; diſſention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> habes laborantem.</hi> Who haſt ſo great diſcorde and diſſention at home in thine owne houſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
               <p>It were happy then I perceiue if theſe Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites were rooted out of the Church, that wee might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée all in one, and not ſtumble at ſmal matters, and let go the greater.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>It were much to be wiſhed that as our reuerend Fathers haue cauſed an vniformity of diſcipline in the Church, ſo they would not onely execute that <hi>Peace</hi>-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:13558:22"/>
                  <hi>Canon,</hi> that none Preach againſte the Doctrine, of another, but preſcribe alſo generant Tennants of our Church to be followed by church-men in the leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Doctrine, that fooliſh and vnlearned queſtions might be ſtayed. And if the Iewes be tyed to their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the Turkes to their <hi>Alcaron: Logitians</hi> to the <hi>Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle: Phiſitions</hi> to the <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of <hi>Hipocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and <hi>Galen: Geometricians</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> compaſſes of <hi>Euclide: Rhetoritians</hi> to the Preceptes of <hi>Tully: Lawyers</hi> to the Maxims of <hi>Iuſtinian:</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Gramarians</hi> to the rules of <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> why not ſuch as are brought vp in Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Schoole to the <hi>Rules</hi> therof; who is a <hi>Lilly</hi> of the Vallies and as a Lilly amonge thornes, ſo is Chriſtes to be amonge the Daughters, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>Are theſe Hippocrites and Newters, ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of diſſention and varieties amongſt vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt of it.<note place="margin">lib. de Iſid. et Oriſid.</note> Wee reade of a crafty King in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who knowing his Enemies the Aegyptians woulde not match him in ſtrength, if they matched in minds and accorded in their Counſell, enioyned each Countrey, the worſhipping of diuers Beaſtes, which were Enemies by Nature, and woulde prey eache on other: And while euery one defended his beaſt againſt the rauine of another, and tooke his Wronges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently it came to paſſe at laſt (ſaith the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ob animalium inimicitias ipſa quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gentes re non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruata infeſta ſibi invicem hoſteſque redderentur.</hi> That
<pb facs="tcp:13558:23"/>by the enmity of their beaſts the people themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares became ſuch Enimyes that hee ſubdued them. Thus, and more then ſo ſubtile is the Prince of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who perceiuing vs to be <hi>Inſuperabiles niſi ſeparabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> impregnable while knit in one mind and iudgment, he brings in <hi>Neuters</hi> and Hypocrites amongſt vs: ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcruing, and faſhionary Bible-bearers, that ſow ſtrange queſtions, as tares among Wheat, and as Idols adore their priua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e opinions, about which while we contend, <hi>Ob opinionum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>micitias re non obſeruata ipſi quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, hoſtes reddimur.</hi> Of this doting on queſtions, and vnneceſſary ſtriefes, commeth enuy raylings, and euill ſurmiſinges through vaine diſputations of men.</p>
               <p>After which (as after No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elties) their eares doe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally itch: giuing themſelues <hi>Athenian</hi>-like, to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as to heare new things,<note place="margin">Actes. 17, 21.</note> and nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing that vnity and true peace, that ſhould be in bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of one father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What is that peace and vnion brethren?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
               <p>It is the mother of <hi>Cremites,</hi> father of <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bites,</hi> and Siſter of <hi>Solitaries,</hi> it is the bond of the Patriarcks, the Chariot of the Prophetes, and the refuge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſties: It is the Calmeneſſe of the mynd, the tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſoule, and ſingleneſſe of the hart.</p>
               <p>It ſtauncheth grudges, quencheth broyles, ſtynteth Garboyles, and pulleth downe the Creſt of pride. Let
<pb facs="tcp:13558:23"/>him therefore that poſſeſſeth it, kéepe it: let him that wantes it, ſéeke it: and him that hath loſt it, go after it: For behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in vnity.</p>
               <p>Which as it was ioyfull for <hi>Dauid</hi> to behold in ſome of his kingdome, for <hi>Ostendebat qui dicebat Ecce</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtine</hi>) he poynted the finger to ſome whom hee ſayde <hi>Behold:</hi> So I wiſh that Pſalme might now bee ſayde as truely <hi>Eccè:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in hunc Pſal.</note> Behold how brethren of one heauenly Father dwell together in vnity.</p>
               <p>I wiſh they that are without might poynt aſbs, as did the Heathen at thoſe Chriſtians in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, and ſay,<note place="margin">Tertul. 39. apo. aduers. Gen.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold how theſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans loue one another.</hi> Not like Hypocrites, in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiall and worldly ſhew, but as becomes true Profeſſors with inward and hearty affection: ſuch as beſéemes the Seruaunts and Sonnes of theyr Mayſter and Maker. Now is high time the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world being ſaid by the prophets, to be ſo néere at hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>How gather they the end of the world is at hand?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe (ſay they) Men doe now as they did when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ud was néere, banquet, eat, drink, buy, ſell, take vſe, or gayne, build houſes and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, Kinges make warres, and manage Armes,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:24"/>miniſters ſtudy to augment their tythes, Diuines knit Sillogiſmes, and the Commons are tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. To conclude, there is no euill which now is not among men: hunger, thirſt, theft, and Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, warres, Peſtilence, Sedition, and want of all that is good.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let the ſame mind be in vs, (ſhall I ſay with the Apoſtle that was in Chriſt) the ſame? Nay I am out of hope of it: He was ſuch a louer of men, as they were but men, that he layde downe his moſt pretious life to the moſt ignominious death, for man his moſt rebellious Traytor. But if not the ſame, yet let the like minde be in vs that was in Chriſt: at leaſt let the minde of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> an Heathen and naturall man bee in Chriſtians: for ſhame of mankinde, let not the minde of Tygers, of Wolues, of Bears, and of Lyons be in vs, leaſt we be <hi>Shame-kins</hi> to mankinde. Nay, let but the minde of theſe to their owne kind, the mind of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to Lyons; of Wolues, to Wolues be in vs; not to hate our mankind, and good enough. But alaſſe when it ſhould be <hi>Homo homini Deus,</hi> Man to man a preſeruer, Now it is become <hi>Homo homini Lupus.</hi> Man to man a deuourer. Euery man hunteth his brother with a net. Yea, whereas all mindes and motions of Enmity are in theſe beaſtes, but ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and peculiar to theyr kynde, they all méete in one Man like Ryuers in the Sea, who is to Man in mind rauenous as a Wolfe, in head crafty as a Fore, in heart fiery as a Tyger, in tongue poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous
<pb facs="tcp:13558:24"/>as an Aſpe, in the euill eye, deadly as a Cockatrice, in bloudy handes cruell as a Lyon: Therefore the Pſalmiſt compareth this man not to one beaſt, but to the beaſtes that periſh. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> blandas conſalutationes, amicos complexus, hilares com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potationes, caetera<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> officia humanitatis;</hi> I ſée indeede (ſaith <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) euery one giue fayre ſpoken and courteous ſalutations, friendly embracings, and congies, merry méetinges, and kind drinking one to another, and other ſuch parts of humanity: <hi>At ô re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indignam</hi> (it is the complaint of <hi>Peace</hi> hir ſelf) <hi>ficta, fucata omnia,</hi> all is fained friendſhip and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. One cannot ſée the leaſt ſhadow of true a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity amongſt men, all is naught but diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deceipt.</p>
               <p>They couer hart-burning, and malice, Enuy, &amp; hatred vnder theſe duties of humanity: cloakes of Curteſie, and faire ſéeming ſhew of piety: They come in ſhéeps cloathing with the name of brother of Friend, Coſin, and Kinſman, <hi>Et astutam vapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rvunt ſub pectore <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulpem,</hi> and within they are rauening Wolues. Where is now a faithfull yoke fellowe that is <hi>Alter idem,</hi> in whoſe eare a man may lay his hart, and his life in his hand: where is a <hi>Nazian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with a <hi>Baſil?</hi> An <hi>Auſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with an <hi>Alipius?</hi> which like a paire of Turtle Doues mourn and reioyce together? where are they that beare out the others burthen, and ſupport each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorough Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e? The Heathen in their daies, tought but eight ſuch faithfull yoke fellowes,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:25"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pylades.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Damon. and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oreſtes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Euryatus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Achilles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pernhous.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pollux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Polynices.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Laetius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pythias.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>But if now the Lord ſhould looke downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vppon the children of men to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand, and ſéeke God in the loue of his neighbour, that of <hi>Dauid</hi> might now be returned, <hi>Ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dem.</hi> There is ſcant a man to bee founde on the earth: If now, as once <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſought an honeſt man in the ſtréet with a candle at noone day: or if as the Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad his Prophet, one ſhould now run too and fro by the ſtréetes of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to know and inquire in the open places there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it be could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rid one man that is faithful to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he might (I feare) in many places returne his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with <hi>Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> Behold I ſought one by one to find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> count, and yet my ſoule ſeeketh, but I find it not: I haue founde one man of a thouſand. And what is the reaſon of this? For that as Chriſtians (ſaith <hi>Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tine</hi>) hauing all one Father which is God:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d de deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>t. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſtian. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1.</note> one Mother the Church, whereby wée are brethren in the ſpirit: we y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t kéepe not the vni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,
<pb facs="tcp:13558:25"/>of the ſpirit in the bond of peace. We would ſéeme Religious, yet ſhew it not in our Workes, carrie bookes in our hands to deceiue the worlde, yet not haue them grafted in our harts to pleaſe God. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man is led by his owne will, followes affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and obſerues the rule of his owne opinion, forgetting, or at leaſt neglecting that of <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctior eſt copula cordium quam corporam,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiores ſunt qui ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quam qui corporibus coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur,</hi> Nearer are they of kin whoſe harts are of affinity in the ſpirit,<note place="margin">lib. 6. diuin. inſtit. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note> then they who are but of lynage in the fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
